[Music]
So we're going to follow
today. So last week we left of a shot at a
section. Right, so others may leave if they want to. The guys who didn't actually
revise
last week's lecture. If you're so
interested and so disinterested, you could leave.
Right, so let's just teach for the six
people who read. Okay, I don't care.
Right, so there was one question. A
last class to show that this actually works. We need
to show that
v is a banal space. Okay, how hard is it to
show that v is a banal space? What is v?
What is v? Capital v? What is the space? We
want to show as a banal space.
Space of all value functions. Okay, well,
value function is a little tricky because
value functions mean that there is some policy
and something that generates that. Right, that need not necessarily be true. It's very
hard to
quantify such a space.  Right so v is the space
of all
functions to satisfy something for us what it's very
simple what the most basic condition is we
put
bonded right so component
where the function is
bonded because of an element here it is rate and then
take off one component of the vector v right
that component will
always be bonded right okay and think of what is
the norm that we are considering here in
ten space so essentially what capital v is it's the
space of
all bonded
what function right space
of all bonded functions right so because we have this
function operating on a
discrete space right so we can just think of
these points in space right but it's
actually function space right it's actually space
of functions right so capital v is a space
of bonded functions right and what is the
norm that we
consider max nom right max nom right and
and what is that we need to  Show if it's a
binary
space it converges right but what we know here
all cosh sequences what does the cosh
sequence say so
you keep growing difference becomes smaller and smaller
and smaller so what does it mean it converges it should be
in the same space right so so what can you tell me about any such
space with max num on it so complete
full space ra I'm not excluding anything
only problem I have is
my function has to be component wise
bonded t the function has to be component wise
bonded
rat and if you look at the t so
basically the idea it ssu I'm saying that my
function are getting as close to each other my
vectors are getting as close to each other
and given the fact that each component wi are all
bonded rat so the limit also has to be
a bonded function and as it's a bad
function it will assist  In this
space, so the other thing to show is that it is bonded
under the equilibrium norm, right under the max
norm, so any is bonded under any norm, okay,
so the tricky part is this is not [an], it's a
subset of any [an], right, what is it a subset of any [an], we I'm just saying
all components have to be bonded, right, so any [an] does not have that
restriction, we could have some components that can
grow unbounded, right, so the only
tricky part here is show that, okay, since I'm talking about bonded
vectors, okay, the
point limit of any bonded vector should also be bonded, right, so
the case [an] I could set
up a situation, I'm considering [an], anti-
bend ...
Sequence like this right so I'm actually
setting up a sequence of bounded functions so
the sequence
event so it's a little tricky to show that
but the idea is that it's going to be a set
of sequences of bounded functions and I'm
assuming the inequality between them is becoming smaller and
smaller infinitely smaller right as it becomes
larger and larger and then for you can't have an
unbounded value it's close
to the bounded value so then finally the limit
exists in this as a
new formal proof for it being a little more complicated
concept
but so next we have to move on to the time
equation with the
value time
equation
and the
notation so about this rate margin o
prime notation last
class so the
actual value of a given state
and action is the margin o
the probability
of all possible a and this we spoke about right so
and or so this is  This is an
eviation Rat so what we are doing is to go from here to here
Ra I am writing this in vector
notation Ra so translate this into
vector notation of a a Pa as
expected value get following Pa Rat
for next immediate step Rat so
ver or so so the
only difference here is here I use asm that you
use a here Rat but here I am asm you
are using a
Pi okay and so this is the probability of
that of the next state following policy
Pa right here again I am asm asm
j and here I am saying v star the
summation is gone Pa Pi no no so I will tell you
right so I am
doing max over a right so for each state
I will get one max over a I will get no
one action a max action let us say that
one action a the max action for each yes right so
what essentially the gives me it gives
me a  Mapping from state to an
action So what is set mapping it's a
policy So that is the policy pi we're talking about But here this is
Ashley componentwise
maximization of this expression So for
every state I will write out this expression
For every state I will find the a That
correspondingly
edit here Rat So for every state I will solve this thing I will find out
what a is Okay
and set t as the max pi
So this max pi is a shortcut for
saying it's componentwise Every a
run max
independently I can also make any assumptions
about the structure of policy pi Ra So for
every state I set arbitrary action s the action
for
pa So this is
my equation written in vector form
So now I have to define this s
operator
So define s t operator T takes in ry
star and does this
computation Give y back
another point in the
space n operator Ashley
lv
and what  We are claiming that v is
the fixed point
of
a right so last class we looked at l pi right which was
the iterative process for the
Balaban equation for v pa now this is the Balaban
equation for v is the star so I've written it like this
rat and then taken this whole operation and
converted it into a single matrix operation
rat and so now the function ll becomes av is this is a
not linear function because
of max is not a linear function can this
writing a looks like it is matrix
multiplication not okay and basically claim your
term
l is a contraction so an el contraction what you get you get all
things for free right so what
you
get is an el contraction
kind of hand waving arg t i banak space
an el contraction so what you get is
a unique fixed point star right
and and el contraction ok so start from some
arbitrary repeated application and convert it to so we get
Both this thing is free so let's look at
showing
this
rate so don't say a star of s it means the
best action to do is at least one of the best
actions to do in
state y again we talk about the grid
world y could go in any combination y could
reach the top
right ness so you could go either right and you could go up any
combination of right and up will
work to get you to the final state right so either
right and up the best action it could be more than one
best action both
of this do not preclude multiple
things being best ok as its just
finding out the value corrupt the best action r so we argue that there could also be
multiple best actions but there can be only one
value correlating to two best actions either way you
go up r you go right or you will
take the same number of steps to reach the goal
right so the value will be the same but you could have
multiple  Policies So I'm not
precluding this This is any one of the two
best pieces you plug in here right like any one
of the best pieces you plug in here
and you compute a star So I'm not saying you have to find
1 par nothing right So this here
I'm picking one such a that is where I'm
deducing from a is equal to a star is equal to
arg max I'm saying a belongs to arg
max Okay so what we really have to
establish is that later on it will be
useful for you doing the assignment that
you don't really have to consider if
caustic policies are one you're not
dealing with MDP at least you don't have to
consider caustic policies for fiat
MDP there will always be a deterministic
optimal policy so it's enough if you only search
for one deterministic policy you don't have
to search for  So caustic policy that we will have to show right what
I will do is I will not do it
in class so I will give you a small
write up to read some of my nuts or make up
write up and put it online so you can read
it from moodle so just to teach you a little
bit of algebra not too much so just to write a
theoretical policy so fit
okay but right now so far I don't ask anything just ask
one action the best
right
and let's ask I have to
function and
yk av operating
on i and l operating n y remember from
discussion in the last class t lv i
function lv i function lv of a i a
component of function and yv acting n
svr i output ok so the function lv i is
not operating on s i the l of you had
confused last class lv i not operating n
of l e something that takes a function an
argument and outputs a function right so
lv i the
function rat y tech y  Apply a on it and
then the resulting function y apply n so
like why y take y apply on it and the
resulting function y apply on s okay so
I'm first making the assumption that av of a
is greater than a of
s okay so what do I need to
show come closer then v s and you rat so
basically what a we did this last class
also we did the same thing so we some one way we
show it and then we flip another way show it
and then we show that for every state as the
absolute value in context then the name also
corresponds to at least the same thing the last
class is wa a a people to customs from last
class so I can just go through this really am just
clarifying this because last class
after the class all of people are asking
me questions about lv ly business so so its
clear right so lv is a  The function ch i
operating n
okay
rat so a star i the one gives you the max
rat sot gives you the max y so I remove
the max and rotate in terms of a
star rat so this is essentially a
of okay so I put less and equal to y so
I'm going to do something on the other term ch i a of
y okay so expand a of y I well right
equal to right so I'm going to do something tricky
with another term so what is the tricky thing that I'm
going to do so
I got rid of the max y also
but in of using the max
correspondingly
a star i the max and v is the function here
but I'm plugging in a star it itself here right so what can you tell me about this it will be less than
the actual max one
l operates on y
you see the so when a is operating on this
right so essentially there is a max over
here  And there will be right here,
but instead of taking the maximum
action, I am taking some arbitrary action
which is a star and paging it in term
for this will be less than the maximum right here, because this difference
will be
greater than this because this in this term is also
the maximum correspondingly in term with something that is
smaller, or this will be greater,
this difference will be greater,
okay, it is
not a final, but a star is a final
for maximizing something, or a
star solution for this,
maximizing this problem, is an oscilloscope.
It is one of the solutions for solving this
problem, not the function, or it may or may not be the solution,
not the function is, so if it is
the solution, then this will be the quality, then it is
not a solution, then this will be less than, okay,
great, so now the advantage  So by doing this I can
start cancelling out all the terms
and try to make this simpler so what I do is end up
with
this so this term is equal
to the same
trick last term so this couple of terms is the difference between the sum of the differences is the maximum difference between the sum of the terms so it becomes
independent of each other so I can
take out and summation and summation how I have so I can do the same thing
and I can put this around the sum so I can start with
zero and minus the minimum difference between the sum of terms and the maximum difference between the sum of terms on the right hand
side for each term and then the whole thing is still the same thing so they are also equal to the maximum difference so I
finally get that so how I'm
solving
an
MDP is how I do it I do it I start
with an arbitrary value function
just keep applying a repeated and up terminal value function
so I have a terminal value function so I will
recover the optimal
policy I  Can I do this all right what I did here
run this new star rasaal go mean optimal
policy I can pick any action arbitrary action
from that form the arg max and take this
optimal action and I could just define some
code of probability distribution tag so just
write down so this is a very popular
algorithm
called value iteration because you start with
value and then iterate over it until you come to the
final convergent value tag so this is or so
for people are wondering about my
programming assignment had management
assignment so value iteration one of the things I'm asking you to do is so just
start
with an
arbitrary value function then repeat
implement a and run so you come to a fix
point the only interesting thing now is what is the 100 more
times have to say
arbitrarily what is the more interesting
point or take about one and I said it's not the
right
answer one do I
stop or  Not the number but I stop it can be a
simple number I just do it several times
okay so I should have some other convergent
test the tells me one it stop rat all I keep doing it till successive
iteration and with in r same you are great I mean but same will not happen same same will take far very close to same policy yes but we not
computing the policy
every time rat policy it is a painful process you have to be
greedy with respect to the value
function every time in every iteration
computing the same policy it becomes a
problem r I am going to compute the policy
in every iteration then it might be a problem because
you have to do additional
computation it may be may not be i mean it is a
call that you have to make but if you want to give
certain guarantees about what will hold when
things converge then you better have
a bound  On the value
function, okay, so we'll come to another
algorithm called policy iteration. We
can work with the space of policies. Okay, but right now, we're just
going to do this with
value functions. Right,
so select some
sum, including two points
for the stopping
criterion, and start the iteration. The next component will return v = a pi ...
A pretty rat, but I'd like to give you a
guarantee on how far away from the star end of the
day it's not necessarily how close and pretty are you so we'll take this
close condition and convert it to a
guarantee on how close you are to the star then and I can't
fight you will be like you're supposed to be like I'm supposed to be like I'm supposed to be like
[music]
[applause]
star